Well, welcome all for a wonderful warm January.
What better to warm yourself than by
the fabulous thing of free government money?
I'm Steve Derzinski.
I've got a bunch of background that I'm going
to go through in a second, but I wanted to
give you guys a little bit
of the history of this particular lecture.
A couple of years ago, I looked around MIT and
I said, why is it that we don't have anything
on really winning SBRs and what the process is
to win them, not just how to fill out forms?
And it turns out that most people provide
it as consulting, and some people aren't really
allowed to say the things that
I want to tell you guys about.
So I decided to just put this together.
I did it.
Last year, we had the ones that I know
about, the three people that applied all won awards,
and actually one company decided to just go
and raise venture capital, and they just closed
a $5 million round.
So hopefully you guys will
be in that same boat shortly.
Okay.
So I'm Steve Derzinski.
I've got my undergraduate
in mechanical engineering from MIT.
I was originally a roboticist, which kind of
gives you a certain mental model of the
world that everything works in feedback.
So you know, we're all going to get
feedback loops, and every time you're trying to control
something, you always have to get the feedback on
it, and make it kind of correct what it
didn't do.
I've got a patent on the space shuttle's robotic arm.
So when the space shuttle's robotic arm was
trying to move solar panels, they would vibrate
like crazy, so we came up with an algorithm to
move it a lot more quickly and with a lot
less vibration.
I then went back to Sloan
and got a Sloan Fellow's degree.
So I have both that kind of weird engineering vibe.
viewpoint and then also an MBA. And in between
those two, I was down at Georgia Tech and I
created what I call the first faculty venture
studio. And yes, it was formed before the Deshpande
Center at MIT. And this is basically a process
that you go through the university and you look
at all the technology they have and you say,
this is great. What are the commercial applications for
it? Our innovation was basically bringing in
fundable CEOs into the university so they could
form companies within our venture lab. So it was
like a university lab, but it was for venture
creation. And that's still going today. You can look
it up online. I think they've done about $2
billion with the startups now. And today
I'm running a co-foundry in Kendall Square, forming
multiple companies from that technology. But in terms
of this class right now, my experience with
federal contracts is about $40 million roughly. Sorry,
this is the $23 million list of all the
federal contracts I've done. And I've done a
lot of research on the federal contracts. And I've
done a lot of research on the federal contracts.
And I've done a lot of research on the federal
contracts. And I've done a lot of research on the
federal contracts. And I will tell you that I was
either the PI or the primary business person on
all of these contracts. So I have interfaced with NASA,
NSF, DOE, ARPA-E for all of these things, as well as
DOD, which is not on the list. But I've done a
ton of work that way. And over the years,
I've discovered kind of this, you know, all money is
not equal, right? There's different colors of
money and there's different motivations for the
funding that you get. And understanding that
before you get into it is really critical.
So I wanted to make a specific characterization
of disruptive technology. A lot of people talk
about, or I did my MBA actually on
technology innovation, which was focused on thinking about
how do you commercialize incremental technology
advances and how do you commercialize radical
technology advances or disruptive technology. And the
classic example, and I'm not going to
go into too much detail on this, but I
think it's really important to understand is that what
you're trying to do is you're trying to get
the right product, right? And you always see these
pulled together is if you have an incremental
technology, then it's very easy to just go and
talk to your customers about what do they want. I
mean, if I just took a generic customer and I
said, what do you want? They would say exactly
what I have right now, but cheaper, faster, and
with better quality, right? I mean, that's like
an easy thing to sell because it doesn't disrupt
their model, right? So commercializing incremental
innovations should be fairly straightforward. What
you're trying to find for is
disrupting crazy innovations or, sorry, commercializing crazy
technology. And it's uniquely positioned in funding
those kinds of activities. So to this point,
one of my favorite quotes from Henry Ford, if
I asked people what they wanted, they would have said
a faster horse, right? Because they all had horses
at the time. They just wanted what they had right
now, just a little bit faster. They wouldn't have said,
I want a vehicle that has four wheels that I
have to start up every day and stick gasoline
in, right? Along those lines, I think that's a good
quote. And one of my favorite lines, Steve Jobs,
another quote I love, which is, what we have found
is that in general, customers don't know what they want
until you show it to them. So now what we're
here today talking about is, great, I've got this
cool technology and I want to reduce it to a
product that I can show to a customer, but where
do I get that funding, right? Let's see. So that
over the years, everyone's talked about the valley of
death over the years. And I have a, you know,
unique view of this. And one is that
governments and universities, there's a ton of money available
to do research on the next cool thing, right?
If you have no application, but you have really cool
research idea, there's a ton of money at
the National Science Foundation, DOE, to go discover
neat things. But if you're in the university, there's
a certain vector that your funds have to go
in. And they have to go towards
finding new interesting things, new interesting research. As
soon as you start doubling down on the same
money going after other things, you're going to have a
lot of money. And if you're looking
for an application and going after commercial, that's
considered not the right use of funds, right? You
have to get different sources of funds to move it
towards the commercial landscape. And then you go
on the other side in the private sector, Wall
Street has a ton of money, right? So if you have
a customer that wants to expand or if you want to
expand your operation and you've got ten years of
financials, there's a ton of sources to do that.
But it's that gap in between and how do you
fund that gap in between that's the real challenge. And
I know there's a bunch of solutions out there, but
I've looked around and I've looked at a lot of
solutions. And I've looked at a lot of solutions.
And I've looked at a lot of solutions. And I've
looked at foundations and angel investing and VCs. And
really what I've come to over all of these
years is that the SBIR is really the best program to
fund that gap. And often when you go and talk to
end customers, they'll say, hey, this is great research.
Where can I buy the product? And then you
sort of have to gulp. There's a lot of work
between this paper that I just got published and actually
having a product that you can play with and understand
how it works. So what I've found is if you
talk to end customers about a disruptive technology and
you don't have it reduced to practice or don't
have it reduced to something that they can use and
try, you're going to just talk to a lot of customers
that don't understand or they're going to be nice
to you or other things. So that's really where the
SBIR comes in and specifically a lot of the programs
that we're going to talk about today. And the way
that we look at this at the Kendall Square cofoundry
is by focusing on these two sort of blue squares.
I call them a technology project if it's a
technology project, it's a technology project if it's a
technology that has a lot of interesting research
dimensions to it, but there's no real customer
that either understands or has been engaged or really knows
kind of how to purchase it or how to even
interact with it at some stage. So in that
mode, you're exploring new applications. And if you're in
this mode of exploring new applications, the worst thing
you can do is take recourse funding, in my
opinion. So this is a
little bit of a different approach.
It's a little bit controversial. So right between
these two, and then on the right-hand side, sorry,
on the right-hand side, we have company projects, which
are, okay, we've got them, you know, we've got a
demo and we've got things that people can use and
we now just need to understand how to fund them more
so that we can refine them, you know, debug them
and get them in a package that the customer really wants.
But that's only after you have clear customer focus.
And a lot of times people, especially in, you know,
around MIT, there's a ton of funding available for
applications. And so, you know, we're going to talk about
equity funding, you know, angels and VCs, that's all
recourse funding. And I want to caution you all
that crossing that line when you're in this exploration
mode can be a little bit crazy because when you're
in this exploration mode and you take recourse funding,
it's like I have an obligation to somebody but I
don't really know what direction I'm going yet. And
you keep in mind I've been doing this for many
decades. So I've seen a lot of oopses in this space.
So if you're on the left side of that line, grants and
non-recourse funding, absolutely. That is the perfect
source of funding to reduce things to practice.
And if you're on the right side of the line
where you have customers and you've got traction, then getting recourse
funding is OK. But I mean, it's absolutely the
way to go. And especially if you need growth capital.
So I know I know I have a lot of I have invested. I
have a lot of investor friends and a lot of them say, oh, no, no,
we like to take technology risks. And then you realize
that maybe that's not such the best way to do it.
Maybe that's not such the best, best idea for your
technology because you still don't know what direction it needs to
go in. I can tell you that they love to invest on the
right hand side when you have customer traction and you just need to
you know, the pump is already going and you need to just
jam more, you know, jam more capital into that pump and keep
cranking it out. So so over the you know, as you sort of
look at all the sources of funding that are out there, what you
come to is that SBIR is the best source of funding
for this exact stage being in this sort of deep technology space.
So.
Yeah. So don't take recourse funding at this stage. And I'm sure
you're getting lots of angels who are like, oh, no, we'll give you
100 grand. Oh, we'll give you 200 grand. You can still take it.
Right. I mean, I don't have any control over you, but I don't
recommend it.
OK, so perfectly designed for this. It's about
four billion dollars of federal funds every year.
And if and that's expended every year, that's given out every year.
So if you were to sort of do the math on that,
you would be able to do the math
on what size venture capital fund that would be.
Venture capitalists give out about a fifth of their of their
total capital under management every year in their new funds every year.
So that would be about a
20 billion dollar equivalent venture capital fund.
And the expectations are simply
that you will do the good.
You'll do the work. There's no expectation of getting
paid back or that you'll be commercially successful or anything.
And I want to point out that some equity investors
do actually view winning an SBIR as a good investment.
They see winning an SBIR as
a positive for their due diligence.
So especially if it's sometimes there's a lot of
DOD people that have some deep, deep technology expertise.
And if they decide to fund you, then that's a that's an indicator
on the outside that says, oh, well, you must know what you're talking about,
because we know this these guys at the DOD and they know, you know, if you're
just not if you don't really have what it takes or if you if you do.
So so that's that's a good thing. All right.
And I wanted to go into real quick
on the incentives of the different funding sources.
Charlie Munger from Berkshire Hathaway
has another favorite quote of mine.
Show me the incentives and I'll show you the outcome. A lot of times, if
you already know what the incentives are, there's no even point in asking the question.
So you guys probably I'm sure you
all know about angel investors and VCs.
The biggest distinction between an angel investor and a VC is an angel investor
is investing their own money so they can write a check whenever they want.
So they can write a check whenever they want.
Right. There's there's no it's like I feel
like right now you seem like a nice guy.
I can write your check. No problem. Right.
A VC actually technically gets money from limited partners.
So they have someone else up
the chain that they respond to.
And so what I'm going to say might sound a little crass,
but it's absolutely true if you think about the structure of the relationship.
OK, so their motivation is to maximize return, get a
big piece of equity and get to a fast exit.
Now, I've talked to a bunch of VCs
and they'll all say, no, no, we're slow investors.
I can tell you that that may be true.
But the question really is the limited partners
that are that have put money in them.
Do they actually feel that they're slow investors?
Maybe there may be a couple
out there that do actually do that.
But by and large, the whole reason why limited partners like big pensions funds allocate
a little bit of money for the VC is because they expect those really high returns.
And the only way you get
returns is that it's return versus time.
So if you stretch the time out, the return
has to go through the roof of the VCs.
So that's the only way you get returns.
The return has to go through the roof in
order to kind of meet the obligation of that sector.
So I still stand by these
these two motivations of a VC.
Now, let's talk about SPR program manager.
Does anybody want to take a
guess at what their first motivation is?
Science?
That would be great. What do
you think their first motivation is, though?
Creating jobs.
Creating jobs. Yeah, those are good motivations.
Those are good. Anybody else?
Using the funds.
Using the funds properly. Yep. Yep.
I would argue that the first motivation of
an SPR program manager is to not get fired.
OK, and I say this sort of tongue in cheek, but it's important to remember when you're interfacing with them
that they're they're not in it to like do you favors and, you know, cut a deal and all that stuff.
Because when you it's it's it's a lot of work.
And when you it's interesting to me to interact with both
VCs, angels and SPR program managers, because it's a very different ballgame.
You know, when sometimes, you know, when you're you're in it,
you're both in it to make a lot of money with VCs.
Right. You both want to, like, make high returns.
And with SPR program managers, they're like so.
So this is the argument for why when you go out and you look to find all
of those things about how to win an SPR proposal, they talk about filling out the proposal correctly.
And you're like, come on, I know how to fill.
I know how to read instructions and fill this out.
But the reason is because if they get a proposal that's awesome and there's something wrong with it and you didn't
read the instructions correctly, they can't technically go back and ask you to correct it, even if it's a minor glitch.
So they have to reject you.
And it's like heartbreaking to do that, because if they do,
then they'll run the risk of losing their pension or other things.
So so that's the number one motivation.
The second motivation is to not be
embarrassed by their decision to fund you.
And I say this also a
little bit tongue in cheek because.
But it's really important because if you come across as a little bit flippant or not
quite professional in the use of funds, then it's going to be like, well, you know what?
There's like 10 other guys behind you
that I can give money away to.
Why should I?
Why should I spend a lot
of time on on this guy?
And then the third is to
fund interesting technologies to progress their agenda.
And there's probably also, you know,
create jobs and everything else, too.
So so I wanted to lay that out.
So you kind of understand when you're going through
this whole process, like, why is it so bureaucratic?
And why do I have to do this?
Why do I have to fill out all this stuff?
And why do I have to fill it out again?
You know, why is it taking so long
for them to make a decision on anything?
So now now hopefully you understand a little
bit of a perspective on their on their motivations.
OK, so so this is I like to do a
little market study like what are we talking about here?
SBIR program, four billion dollars.
This is just the phase one awards from 2022.
And I did look to see
if there was new information available.
This is the latest data
we have from the federal government.
And just to give you kind of the idea of how many,
you know, each agency funds and kind of how much they have obligated.
So I said four billion dollars.
For those of you paying attention, this is only eight hundred
and thirty eight million dollars, but it is only phase one.
So and you can see here that like the Department
of Transportation funds, 12, probably not a big program there.
They have a pretty small budget.
And you can see the DOD is the is
the big beast here with with the maximum amount.
And also it's interesting just to see kind of.
You know, the Department of Commerce,
thirty nine awards and thirty nine companies.
Nobody doubled up.
But some of these other ones like
DOD, there's quite a few doubling up there.
Right.
Anyways.
OK, so let's look at the phase two.
Phase two numbers look pretty similar.
And this is where you get the four point
four billion dollars total phase one and phase two.
You know, you can see the average
award size from that from 2022 as well.
OK, so hopefully all you guys saw the notice that the prerequisite
was to watch that video by Ben Schrag of the National Science Foundation.
If you didn't, you can go back to the
calendar, the IEP calendar and click on the link there.
It's about 20 minutes long.
It's perfectly you know, he just goes through
the basic stuff of what you got to do.
He answers all the questions about the administrative process, what sites to register
with, how long does it take and how does the NSF do their applications?
So as well as we'll talk about in
a second, there's a big difference between that.
All these agencies and their SBIR offerings.
We will have next.
This is the intro class.
And then on Wednesday, we're going to do the advanced class where we're going to talk
about a lot more cool stuff about review process and about AI use and application process.
And Ben has agreed to to call in on that.
So so if you guys want to get your questions ready for
Ben Schrag, he's been at the National Science Foundation for 12 years.
I think.
Maybe longer.
Great guy and very, very
open to kind of helping out.
He did.
I did send him the registration list of all
you guys is about 70 of you that signed up.
And he said, very impressive.
So he's also a nice guy, too.
OK, so let's talk about
the federal funding aspect of it.
The the point that I want to make with this federal
funding and if you don't know, it's like 3.2 percent of all.
Articles about5 out of 40
are written by the central bodies.
That, by the thousands, who, they might be
but it's okay.
I'm going to take this one from Alex
messages that go out to the central Solar's wall.
These are brought in from organiz scanner.
You can double click these.
It's amazing to see this do it.
So I'm going to right an image of this.
is that even though it's called SBIR,
and I call it SBIR
because the National Science Foundation calls it SBIR,
and they were the first agency to have this program,
the DOD guys call it SIBR.
So if you hear that, SIBR,
it's like they pronounce out SIBR.
SIBR and SIDR, I think, S-T-T-R.
And that's just an example that says
just because it has the same name
doesn't mean it's the same in all agencies.
In fact, it's very different across all agencies.
I think the only thing that's the same
is the sort of percentage of the budget that's allocated.
So whatever the DOD's extramural budget is,
they've got to allocate that percentage to that program.
And then I think it
carries the name within the DOD,
but then how it's implemented is very different,
and I've got a bunch
of slides on that as well.
So just so you don't know, it's Phase I.
You have to win the Phase I
in order to qualify to apply for the Phase II.
Typically, it's like a 10% to 15% success rate
on winning the Phase I,
and then it's about a 50% success rate
on winning the Phase II
after you've completed the work on the Phase I.
And then commercialization.
So there's federal funding at Phase I,
federal funding at Phase II,
and there's no federal funding at Phase III.
So a lot of people are like,
what's the point of commercialization?
The point of commercialization is to track the data
on how you've performed so they can report back later.
NSF has a similar model,
and a lot of programs have this,
and I just want to point out this Phase IIb,
which is even though I said
there's no federal funding,
there's no federal funding at Phase III,
with the exception of Phase IIb, right,
which isn't technically Phase III,
but it's shown here on the Phase III side.
It's a two-to-one matching of private investment,
and you have to get at least a million dollars
of private investment.
And I actually did this a few years ago,
so I'm familiar with the process.
And since we were just talking about
non-recourse and recourse funding,
that million dollars does need to be recourse funding
because you can't do things like,
hey, I'll just loan myself a million dollars,
get a half a million dollars
from the NSF to match it,
and then I'll pay for it.
And I'll pay myself back immediately, right?
They figured that out.
So you can't play games like that.
You actually have to get, you know,
and there are letters of support
that have to come from the investors
that show how they actually structured the investment
and put it into your company
so that you can get
the half a million dollar match.
And it's up to a half a million dollars, right?
So if you only get 250K,
you get 125,000 of match from the Phase IIb.
Eligibility for profit.
You can't be a nonprofit and get NSF.
That's fair.
Fewer than 500 employees,
owner controlled by US citizens,
and the startup or established companies are fine.
That's all fine and good.
That's what the law says.
But let's look at like who actually wins them.
And this is the number of employees.
This is from FY01.
It's the DOD winners.
But it's still relevant today.
So occasionally they'll fund a one person company.
So if you're one person
and you have a crazy idea
that you want to do, you know, there's a chance.
More than likely they want to do two to nine,
nine person company, right?
That's kind of like the sweet spot, right?
Somebody that's kind of does the business side,
somebody that kind of does the technology side,
or maybe your two technology nerd founders
that happen to be social.
Social nerds.
Those are always good.
Okay. By definition.
Okay. Let's see.
Okay. So this is where I want
to really split the SBIR program into two parts.
When you start to dive into the agencies
to really get the solicitations
that you want to apply
for, I want you to think
about them in two buckets.
One is market driven agency
and the other is mission driven agency.
So a market driven agency
does not have the customers internally
to the agency.
They have them, you know, the marketplace is the customer,
right?
So a great example of a
market driven agency is the National
Science Foundation or the Department of Energy,
where they see the technology you have.
They understand how it, you know, how great it is.
But they need you to go out and sell it
to somebody that's an important distinction
between a mission driven agency
like the Department of Defense.
The Department of Defense is like, we're at war.
We have a theater of war.
We have immediate needs of like super awesome batteries
for our troops and we are the customers.
Well, we and all of
our defense contractors are the customers.
So we are going to define exactly what we want.
So what you find, what this boils down to is
that in a market driven agency
SBIR program, you'll get these kind
of like do something.
You know, you're going to get a job.
You're going to get a job.
You're going to do something in optics.
You know, do something cool in optics
that customers really love, right?
And then you get like on the
DOD side of things, you get things
like we need a battery that fits
in this pack that has this kind
of temperature controls on it
that it'll last for this long
and only, you know, only
weighs this much or, you know,
is below this number of things.
So it's far more specific in its offering.
So it becomes a lot more challenging for you guys
to match kind of whatever
you're working on with the solicitations
on the mission driven side of things.
The opportunity though, of course, is if it's harder
for you to match, it's harder for everybody to match.
So there's probably fewer competitors in that.
And in fact, I mean, if you look
at the numbers, you'll see that if there is,
you know, in a very
specific solicitation, if there's a broad,
you know, a broad offer,
sometimes they have these broad announcements
where it's like, oh, we
want to do something, you know,
propose something really cool to us.
And you find that it's a lot
harder to win that because there's just
so much more applications in that space.
So and of course, NASA is a
mission driven agency too because trying to go
to Mars, right, they're trying to
get stuff up in the air.
Yo.
Yeah, go ahead.
This is your interpretation or
is it on their website somewhere?
This is America's Seed Funds interpretation.
That is, yeah, that's right from the website.
And this is also from the NSF website.
Yes.
Yeah, I'll post them to the WhatsApp group.
And I apologize.
I blocked out the middle section.
We have done it once, which is really important.
There was another mine as well.
So the NFS and USAID, the
National Development Party were trying to
promote this放 ex regulation which is pretty common there,
where you say Lana will kick
in with bugs that can make environment
bear wondering about protecting you
from combiners like, you know,
water milhões, Seo, fogs, tax害 loیں videos and user's rights
machines, these kind of stuff.
But this is very medium top nutrients.
These all bring in vetri模sic oxal.
Right.
the money go do your scope of work
and then write us a report when you're all
done and you know and and you
already have all the money so hopefully the
money was spent properly and everything else
a contract on the other hand is
okay we agree that this is the work that
we want you to do why don't you go ahead
and get started and here's some
milestone payments that we're gonna make
or it's a reimbursable contract where you
actually have to do the work submit
an invoice and get paid the reason
why I make this distinction is because when
you guys go to apply when you've like
talked about like why does it take so
long for me to get this this
grant approved and it's because once they say
here's your award here's the money there's
not a lot of recourse right so
they there's a lot of due diligence
upfront before you get to that crap
grant point on the contract they're
still going to be due diligence upfront
but once it's engaged it's kind of
like you know if something happens mid
project they can easily pull the plug if
they need to and there's not so much
money expended on that
OK great so we are out of
time here's a chance for the next question
my question and not only for myself but
for the rest of the panel and all the
models I think that the thing
that was talked about was darn it
I mean I'm not really sure how the Bob
I'll start but it looks like we had two
questions in the chat so I'm not going
to go into all the different ones but
I think there's a question on the
way you deal with fee training and it's
that I think it's important to stop
and for fra Eckhardt there's a frontOne
But it's also important for you to remember that
it's not just going to be the program manager
that's going to review it, it's going to be
people who understand the industry. And you have an
opportunity in the application to say like, these
are our direct competitors, do not get anyone on
the review panel from that. And they take
that extremely seriously. So I would include that in
your application if you're worried about that. And
then I mentioned kind of the research topics are
specific as or broad, and then whether or not
they provide gap funding, and whether or not the
communication can be restricted, like specifically on mission
or if it's open. So kind of lines up
naturally with sort of the, you know,
mission driven market driven balance. Any questions on
that? This is just a more updated view of kind
of the real numbers of what the agency budget is.
And this is on, I mean, SBIR.gov has a
lot of this information automatically, but I wanted to give
you this information and then give you my
experience and color on top of it. So
if you want to go back and redo these slides, you
can go back to the SBIR.gov and get all the data
from there. One of the strategies we're going to
talk about on Wednesday is kind of thinking about
the timing of things. So, you know, the benefit
of SBIR is you don't give away any equity funding,
right? But the challenge of SBIR is that,
you know, time is a vacuum, right? It's like,
are you guys done reviewing that
yet? What's going on? You know,
there's so many things going on in the world
of federal government, but this is kind of the pace
they operate under. And if you don't
know, the federal government's annual budget closes
September 30th every year, and then a new
budget starts October 1, at least it's supposed to.
And typically a lot of these processes are
driven towards kind of making sure that all
of the awards are allocated by September 30th.
Not always, sometimes they sort of spill over.
But if you think about kind of how
these solicitations come out and when you want to
apply for them, you know, it's kind of a
very, very complex process. And so, you know, I think
that's kind of the, you know, the, you know, the,
you know, the, you know, the, you know, the, you know,
just keep these things in mind because the last thing
you want to do is say, oh, I'm ready to
apply for that NIH grant. Like, oh, well, the
window just closed like last week. So now I've
got to wait another six months or something
to do that. As you think about these dates,
we can also talk about, you know, applying to
multiple ones so you can see kind of how they,
how they ramp up and whether or not you want
to hear from one before you apply to another one.
I usually don't recommend that. I usually just
recommend you just go for it. Yeah. Okay. Yep.
Oh, yeah. Yeah. So, so specifically for the DOE
and DOD and some of the ones that are mission
driven, they're going to have very specific
topics or solicitations. I mean, topic and solicitation
are kind of the same word and they do
what's called like a pre-release. So the yellow and the
green areas they'll send out kind of these are
the, these are the solicitations that we want to
officially open on the official date when the
green bar turns, when it turns fully green.
And that's, that's to sort of test mark
it, their solicitation ideas. Sometimes they pull
them back because they realize, oh, you know,
somebody else, like, I think, I think frankly, inside
the DOD, I don't know this for a fact,
but I think what happens inside the DOD is
they post solicitations and then like some other agency
over here is like, Hey, we already have that
solved. You don't need to fund that. So, and you
know, because there's such a gigantic operation,
they don't necessarily talk to each other. Right.
So, so there's all kinds of things like
that. So that's why they have a pre-solicitation period.
And then, and then when it's open, so, so I
should say that, uh, when the topic is, uh, when it's
like on pre-release or if it's a topic release,
you have the opportunity to talk to the program
manager directly and talk about the solicitation a lot
more freely and openly, as soon as it's locked
down, they, they like say, you can't ask me
any more questions or any questions you ask have to
be publicly posted. So everybody can see all
the questions. So that's kind of your opportunity to
talk to them about, about, you know,
specific issues you might have or specific opportunities.
Yes, sir.
ATTS has two different ones. Um, would you apply,
is there a
way to apply to both the
R&D contracts or the other options?
Good question. Uh, all of these things are
constantly changing. So I like to take the
approach, especially for stuff that takes a long time
to just be aggressive and like apply for as
many as you can and then pull them back. I know
a lot of people are like, oh, that's a lot of
extra work for potentially no gain, but you know,
you'd rather be in the game. Right. And then,
and then decide to not play then, then
to just like step aside from the beginning. So
I think that's a good way to do it.
Yeah.
We'll get into that in one second. There
is, there is some certain, there's some finance,
there's some federal laws that you have to be aware
of. So as I said, you don't want, you know,
you don't want to go to jail and your,
and your, your, uh, program manager doesn't want to lose
their job. So, um, yeah. And, and
actually specifically to that point, um, eligibility,
and usually I do this talk for, uh, for
MIT students that are currently in school or maybe
a postdoc. So you have a current situation right
now, but you're looking to start a company and you'll
want to apply for one of these things. Eligibility
is determined at the time of award, which is not
the time that you submit the proposal. And it's not
the time that you hear back from them on the
reviewers. And it's not the time that they're
asking you for due diligence questions. It is
the time of award that you have to be
employed or whatever you say in your application. And it's
totally fine for you to say, I'm at the university. And
my plan is to start a company once I get out
and I'm applying for this. And here's the
team that I've put together. Um, that's important.
Uh, the other one is the PI is not required to
have a PhD or MD. A lot of people think that's
true because the data shows that often the PI has
a PhD or MD, um, because they're required to have
expertise and oversee the, um, scientific and
technically the project, right? If you have a,
you have a state statement of work, you have a,
you have your R and D plan and somebody has to
oversee and manage all of that stuff. And
if they're not technically kind of like, like well
known within that space that you're, you're doing
the work in, then, then you're not really qualified.
So,
typically the easiest way to do that is
to have a PhD. So, but it's not required.
Um, okay. So this is to your
question. Applications may be submitted to different
agencies for different work for similar work,
but you cannot get an award from different
agency for Duke duplicate projects. In fact, that last
bullet lands you in jail. So, so it doesn't
really give it much, you know, that, that
that's really bad. Um, when you apply to multiple
different agencies, um, for the similar stuff, it
specifically asks you, have you applied to other
stuff? So, so, um, and then you have to
apply to multiple different agencies for the similar stuff.
So, so, and there's a strategy that, you
know, that, that we can talk about on Wednesday.
Um, but I will just tell you, I, I
don't usually recommend doing that unless it, unless there's a
lot of synergy, unless it totally makes sense that like
the NIH has this cool thing and I need the
NSF to fund some software part of this, of
this biotech, you know, like if you have some related
technology and you want to really be aggressive and kind
of apply for both of them to sort of fund
two different parts of the same product, you know,
that you can put things together like that. Um, so
it is, you can totally apply the same technology
to two different agencies. You have to disclose it
to both of them. And once you get under award, you
have to make a decision. Am I going to take that
one or that one? So, so, I mean, I
guess you're, you're, you're sort of upping your game, right?
If it's a 15% success, then you're, then you've
got two of the same thing and maybe it's 30%
success. Yes, sir. Uh, first point, I'm really
struggled with the answer to this. Um, you have
to have an incorporated company when you submit
the application. Um, and then you have to have
a full-time job. So, um, so if you watch Ben's
video, you have to, um, you have to register with
all of those agencies. And I think part of
that registration means you have to have some kind of
an entity. It can be, it can be a, you know,
your own sole source schedule C company. So you can do
it under your social security number. So then
following on that, uh, you might, for students
and postdocs, how do you recommend people
navigate, incorporating, and dealing with the company?
So I'm going to repeat that question and then
I'm going to not answer it. So the question was,
how do you navigate the conflict of
interest office? Uh, that's really challenging. And
that's a subject of the lab you're in the
department that you're in. Um, a lot of some
departments are like, Hey, that's great. That's kind of
what we want to do. Other ones are like,
no, no, no. We have plans to commercialize that
already. You can't take that on your own, right?
So that becomes this huge,
huge challenge. Um, so I don't have a
good answer to you. I think it's always difficult,
right? We're trying to get technology
commercialized here and not deal with politics,
but unfortunately humans are involved in everything.
So there's always going to be politics.
Yes, sir.
I would like to ask about the PI, uh,
do you need to be national, uh, permanent residents
in the United States or can it
be, can it be under a visa?
So I'm going to answer that question
in two ways, and I'm totally going to
caveat it, meaning I could be wrong, but
the company itself, as I mentioned in the eligibility
stuff has to be 51% owned by us citizens
or permanent residents, the PI, the work needs to be
done inside the United States for most agencies.
And I've seen some exceptions to this sometimes,
but it's been kind of weird. And I didn't really
understand, like, I've got a guy who's going to be
in Israel for the summer and he wants to do
some, you know, there's like, you know, he's not a us
citizen, but he's one of these key guys. Um, and so,
um, and so, um, and so, um, and so, um, and so,
um, and so, um, and so, um, and so, um,
and so, um, and so that's a hard question, good hard
question, which I don't have the answer to. So,
yeah. Um, so okay. So one quick thing on SBIR
versus STTR. I don't want to go too far into
this cause we'll talk about that on Wednesday, but, um,
the SBIR permits you to have a research
institution partner and the STTR requires you to
have a research institute partner. So I've done
both. I can tell you that the overhead associated
with the university, kind of to your point
about conflict of interest, how do you resolve that?
How do you get a clean license?
Becomes very challenging.
So I know we're sitting here at MIT.
Love MIT.
I think if you took a $300,000 phase one
and you took 30% of it, which is like 90K,
and you gave it to MIT, it would quickly
cut down to about 45K, maybe even less,
for the actual researcher to do the work.
So it becomes really challenging to do that.
Unless if you really want to engage a university
and they have some fantastic equipment or some fantastic
people that you can't get
access to otherwise, in which case
you can view that kind of process as table stakes.
If you want to get in the game and you
want to use this great equipment,
then that's the reason why we're here,
because it's not cheap to run this place.
What I usually recommend people do
if you do want to engage in a university
is to apply for an SBIR.
And then you can actually take 30%
Of the phase one and
outsource it to your research institute
if you want.
And you can do that through consulting agreements
and other things that are a little bit easier
to kind of get through.
But you probably still have the same conflict of interest
challenge with that one as well.
The award is always made to the small business.
So that's a great thing, because then that
puts you in control of receiving the funds
and then paying the university as opposed
to begging the university to make its payments.
Yes, sir.
I have a question.
I've seen some SBIRs where there's
a clear difference with the STTR.
There's like 30% more.
Oh, like the award amount is 30% more?
Yeah.
You've made 70 or something, and then they
put in more, 30% more.
But I've seen others where it's like you choose,
but it's the same budget.
So it's kind of like,
OK, I could be a .
But at the same time,
I've heard that you're more likely
to get awarded if you have an STTR.
What's your take?
Yes.
So you took the words right out of my mouth.
So it is more challenging to get an STTR.
But the same thing I was saying earlier,
if there's more hoops to jump through,
there's going to be far fewer applicants,
because most people are going to be like, forget this.
And then, in fact, I've heard rumors
that there's a lot of sources of funding
that have to go into STTR
that they just can't get anybody
to apply for, because it's
just not a lot of money
and it's challenging.
So it's like, if one person
applies for it, they'll win it.
Right?
I mean, it's got to
be meritorious and all that stuff.
It can't be, I'm not talking about just putting together
a napkin or anything.
And does it mean for phase 2 of SBIR?
Well, you have to have a
phase 1 to get a phase 2.
So however you came into phase
1, if it's SBIR or STTR,
then that would define how you go to phase 2.
So we heard this, like, if
we are in an STTR right now,
and it's like, if phase 1, and then it
seems like we can apply for
phase 2, we get the invitation.
But if phase 2 is, someone came from an institution
and said, no, you have to
go with a part, with an institution.
And we were like, well, but this is an SBIR.
We were not sure that we
would even migrate to an STTR.
It may have been a matter of budget.
Yeah, I'm not sure.
I'm not sure.
But I mean, that situation, there's
a lot of those situations.
So you've got the SBIR program and STTR program.
And as I said, they get whittled down and converted
into however the agency wants to run
them, so it may be that there's a specific challenge
that somebody has in a department
and they need this funding to do it.
I don't know.
So that may be what you're running into.
OK, so I wanted to
go into the proposal submission details,
sort of how to win these things.
And it's typically a 25-page proposal.
They usually don't accept unsolicited proposals.
And they evaluate it, number one,
based on the technical merit.
So you guys are going to
love this if you're a technical nerd.
And then number two on kind of the other sort
of commercial merit and the firm's qualifications.
I will say that I say this to all the,
I'm going to do a lecture
on the nuts and bolts class too.
But a lot of times,
I do some mentoring at MIT
for student project teams.
And a lot of times
when people look at grant programs
or awards, and they're like, well,
we can get this award for $5,000.
Yeah, but we need like
300 grand to do this thing.
What's the point in doing that award?
If you're a team that's just getting together,
and you're just a bunch of individuals,
if you can do something together under a cohesive unit
and say, we won this award as a team,
that kind of adds credibility to this next phase, which
is kind of like talking about the firm's qualifications.
Well, if you just come in
with three people that just put
the firm together, the firm doesn't have any qualifications.
It's just three guys that decided to come together
and put a name on top of our heads.
So I would say I wouldn't necessarily
poo-poo some of the smaller ones just
to give you guys a chance
to kind of put together a business.
Yeah, OK.
Let me keep going here.
So this is directly from the National Science Foundation
research.gov proposal preparation process.
There's a whole bunch of stuff in here
that you guys can all
figure out how to fill out.
It's all details around it.
But what I wanted to
focus on was the project description
and then the letters of support.
And this is specific to the National Science Foundation.
These two areas are the most important things for you
to spend most of your time on.
Everything else you should be
able to just plug and chug.
I mean, read the instructions
and do it correctly, of course.
So a project description is 15 pages.
It has an elevator pitch.
It has a commercial opportunity, company and team,
a technical solution, and the technical merits R&D plan.
So this is for a phase one.
This is the first time that an agency would
fund this project or this technology.
So the focus of a lot of the work
needs to be on the technology solution and the technology
merits R&D plan.
So there's a bunch of other stuff
that we put together, commercialization
and all kinds of ideas.
At the phase one level, we're going
to specialize in other areas.
All the SEC has sixth level projects.
So what you're going to do
on the first level level lifecycle
set, I'm going to do an hour and a half
of like examples of what all
of that is going on in terms
of what we need to do in terms of what
are the contenido opportunities.
We're going to be focusing on all of these aspects.
Not only do we do Seth down below,
but we're going to be focusing on what
are the actual requirements around using technology нам
So it's probably a big upload period
immediately going to take place
like a week ahead of when
we start writing the statement.
And then last adjustedm
good customer that says that looks interesting
you know I would buy it if
it were reduced to practice in this
way that would be great investors with
serious interest in the outcome that
means like we read their business plan
we love what they're trying to do
we see a huge opportunity in the marketplace
but they have some significant technical challenges
and they are just the team to
do it right like that would be the
ideal letter of support from an investor and
proving that they actually like know
what they're doing and then partners who
invest after successful outcomes so if there's
if you need to like a path to
market and you need a part a serious
couple of partners in order to get to
that marketplace those guys along the way
saying that you talk to them is a
great letter of support so what are
bad letters of support there's way too many
consultants who get paid from the fund
and it's kind of like what's the point
in telling me you support this project
of course you do right an investor with
no knowledge of the technology so some
people are just like yeah you should
fund these guys they're a friend of mine and then
suddenly you're like oh I'm not sure what
I'm doing I'm not sure what I'm doing
and then you're like oh I'm not sure
what I'm doing I'm not sure what I'm doing
or congressman who want to support
the companies in their district I there's
plenty of these I don't recommend them but
they don't hurt so you know if you
want to do them that's fine I mean
I consider them a bad letter of support
but maybe this is Steve's opinion here
okay questions oh sorry I've had to take
this spam likely or scam likely call
questions on any of that stuff so far
yeah yeah yeah yeah so good question
on the stt Vincent this product for the
you know on the other side so there was
a couple of things like that so on the
else we're next year's i think
know how to negotiate so good question
um and i think the click review task n
we'll go to twitter ago and be like hey
how did you choose this because the
process tutor and the plan tutors have
been
for the phase one to an outside research institute partner.
In other words, 66% of the technology and the innovation
has to be with the small business firm.
That's the reason why it's an SBIR.
When it's an STTR, it's like some of the technology
expertise can be with the company,
but a lot of it is probably at the university,
which is why there's a minimum 30%
for the research institution, right?
Which means the small business
gets 70% and then the 40%.
So that, you know, there's some gap between those two.
If you hit the minimums on both sides,
you have some gap to fund other things, right?
So, but that has to be in the budget.
So a lot of times you, it helps with negotiation.
So if you're engaged with a national lab, for example,
I've done a bunch of work with DOE's national labs.
You know, you kind of go through the,
you don't have to worry about negotiating.
You just be like, well,
this is defined in the SBIR.
That's how much we're gonna do, so.
Sorry, keep going.
Yep.
So the STTR, the 40%
is for the small business companies.
So that's the minimum for the small business concern.
Is that the maximum or is that the minimum?
That's the minimum for the small business concern
and 30% for the research institution.
Oh, okay.
Yeah, yeah.
So the total is only 70% and
you have 30% of slop in between.
So you could do 40% for the research institution
if you want, or you could do 50-50, right?
That's within the range.
Any other questions?
Oh, okay.
Yes?
So I heard that there's a, you know,
basically there is some kind
of markup for like the old,
you know, the overhead.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's why I was saying one of the challenges
is with the research institution for an STTR,
you know, if you have a $300,000 phase one award,
130% of it goes to the research institution,
that's $100,000, but then you gotta multiply it by,
basically take a half of it and that's the amount
that actually can go to do the research.
The other half of it goes to overhead, typically.
I mean, just rough numbers.
Maybe even more than that in some places.
I don't know, does anybody
know what MIT's overhead rate is?
I don't know.
I think 59.
Okay.
Okay, any other questions?
Yes?
Can you explain the timeline of different institutions?
Yeah.
If I want to choose what,
how many months you suggest that is minimum
for the first time writing a grant for that company?
That's a good question.
So if it's the first time writing a grant
and you're going after a broad solicitation,
I mean, you can get started on it.
It's typically like two months, I think,
is if you already have the technology
and you know what it is
and you want to put it
in the right format for this,
I think two months is
about the right amount of time
that people allocate for it.
That's for a broad one,
but if you have to
go into the specific solicitation topics,
then it becomes a lot more challenging
because you have to make sure that your technology
matches whatever's in that solicitation.
So it might take an extra month or so
to kind of make sure that it's focused on that,
especially if it's your first time around.
Any other questions on this one?
Yes, sir.
So for the letters of support,
let's say that you are in a phase one
and there's this specific department
that is actually going to buy your technology
and you want to get more resources
to actually finish that project.
Mm-hmm.
Do their letters of support
will be useful for the NSF as they are?
For example, the letter of
support being from the government?
Yeah.
So it's a customer at the end.
That's why it...
I think it would be fine.
A lot of times, a
lot of these things, it's like,
did you actually talk to a customer in phase one?
Which is kind of unusual, right?
But a lot of times that's important.
If that customer is so
tight that they have a conflict,
then that's a concern, right?
If they're too close to the technology, then it's like,
okay, well, this is just your friend, right?
So I've done several where
there have been prominent professionals,
professors from lots of universities around
that have given letters of support, not as customers,
but just as technology advocates to the baseline technology,
which has been great.
Because one of the things that you'll realize
is that the reviewers, when they sit in a room,
they have 20 of these proposals
that they got to read through.
And really what they do is
they just go through the proposal themselves.
They don't go to a website
and go do extra research on stuff.
And that's probably the most
important thing for you to recognize
is that they've got to review 20 of these things.
The easiest thing in the world is to say no.
So they're just looking for reasons to
say no on any of these items.
And if it takes extra work
to go and like advocate for you,
they're not your friend, right?
They're there to just do the review.
So what you want to do is make
it very easy for them to say yes.
So if there's a bunch
of letters in there that say,
this is great technology, I'm
a well-known person in my industry,
and I say this is great technology, that's great.
Because then they don't have to go
out and like talk to anybody else.
They just see it right there in the package.
So all right.
Yes, question in white.
There is one agency of grants
that you recommend us better than others?
One which?
I didn't hear that.
One kind of agency of grants
that you recommend us better than others?
One agency.
Well, I love the NSF.
So what can I say?
I mean, I have some funding from the NSF.
But it's really a match.
So I wish they would rename it SBIR.
I guess SBIR has the brand
name, so everybody knows what that is.
But within each agency, there's a lot of different things.
Like for example, I know some people
that really have done a bunch of research
and have a bunch of collaborators
within the specific Air Force Research Lab.
And so therefore, the DOD and the
solicitation that come out that match their stuff
are a perfect match for those guys, right?
So it's like, why would you go
to the NSF and try and convince somebody
that you have some big commercial
when I have something that's ready-made
for that solicitation?
So it's really kind of a custom question.
If you are like, I have a
cool idea, and it's super techno nerdy,
and I think there's a commercial market for it,
then the NSF is sort of designed to fund that.
I mean, that's the reason why
they kind of came into this.
I will tell you that they do like to fund,
and they actually make a preference to first-time companies.
So if it's your first-time company
and you want to do first-time funding,
that's kind of their sweet spot.
They prefer to do that.
In fact, if you go back a second
or third time, it's kind of like, eh.
We already got you going.
Now you're supposed to be on your own.
Any other questions?
Otherwise, we'll keep going.
Yes?
So if we write two grants, for example,
DOD NIH, there are two different things.
For NIH, you're looking at
either something, but same company.
Of course, the product at the end
is the same thing, but two aspects.
We can only accept one of them.
No.
So thank you for asking that question.
The question is, if we have two grants,
we have two proposals that have different scope of work.
So like I'm doing software development over here,
and I'm doing, I don't know, drug
discovery over here, or whatever it is.
Those are two different proposals.
So the distinction is if
I take the exact same proposal
and I just change NIH to DOD over
here and I apply the same thing here,
so it's the same, I'm doing software development here,
same person, same thing doing software development,
and innovating the technology in the
same way, that's what you can't do.
And a lot of people have done that.
It sort of makes sense.
It's like, well, if my chances of winning are 15%,
let me just invert that and
submit it to six different agencies,
and one of them will hit, right?
You can do the math on that, right?
So yeah.
And in fact, I think
I like that as a strategy.
If you have a product and
it has multiple technologies that influence it,
you can certainly go and find a
bunch of sources of funding from different SBAs.
And as soon as you get
your company registered and everything else
and kind of go through that process,
that's kind of a big highlight.
And I think that's a big part of the
reason why I've done a lot of federal government work
is because it takes a long time to get
you up over that hump in the first place.
And once you're there, it's kind of like,
I might as well just keep figuring out
who else needs my solution that can be solved.
Yeah.
Unless anybody else has any other questions?
She's already got two down, so yeah.
Go ahead.
About the team.
Yeah.
Should they be officially registered in the
company as part of the employee's team?
Yeah.
As part of the employees?
Because for many startups, one person quit their day job.
The others support, they spend time,
but officially they are working with them.
So are they okay?
Because of the limitations of their primary employer,
they don't go officially in the system.
Right.
I got you.
So the distinction is, and this goes
to the budget and to the application.
So the question was, if somebody's outside and
they are going to come work at the company,
once you get funding, how do
I put them into the proposal?
If they are one of the key people
that you need to do the technology work,
so they're like a named
person on the budget that says,
I need, you know, whatever,
120 hours out of this guy,
then it's a harder question because
then you have a real challenge around,
are they actually a full-time
employee of the company or part-time,
you know, depending on how much
time you put in the actual proposal,
then they need to be in
the company at the time of award.
Yeah.
So if they are just
kind of one of these extra,
so a lot of budgets will just say, you know,
like computer software developers or something, right?
Like they're just extra, you
know, instrumentation specialists or something.
Those aren't as critical to kind
of to sort of winning the proposal.
Then you can leave it at time,
you know, you can do it after reward.
In fact, it's not that critical.
So it's really a function of whether or not you,
and if you use the
bio, someone's bio in your proposal,
then you're saying that these people are adding
to the team and adding to the credibility.
And that's part of the decision process.
So they have to be in
the company at the time of award
because that's what they made their decision on, right?
They're like, well, here's what they want to do.
They've got this person who has this
background and is perfectly matched to do that.
And they've got budget allocated to make them
do the work that has to be contained in.
So you have to figure out how to get
them in the company at time of award, I guess.
Okay. Yes.
One more question, then we're going to get on here.
Yeah.
If people have written,
articles, magazines, things about us,
which they have experts in the field,
would it be better to use that article or
ask that person to write something specifically for the grant?
Well, so you can always put
press in the proposal if you want.
I'm thinking, I mean, if
you're going for a phase one,
that's usually like, you have press already?
Like that's pretty far advanced.
There is COVID in some of the court systems.
Yeah.
I mean, you can certainly add it,
but I guess, I guess,
you know,
what it's supposed to be for is for
deep technology development that's not been commercialized yet.
So if you're already commercialized,
then it's like,
maybe we should be doing something else.
So, okay.
All right.
So, so this is the right way
to get started on this whole process.
So before you spend any money on
creating a company or any administrative time,
you can do a project
pitch for the National Science Foundation.
And then you can do a,
you can do a project pitch for the National
Science Foundation or a quad chart for everybody else.
And then actually you can do a
quad chart for the National Science Foundation too.
So why,
why do I say this?
Why am I telling you to do this right now?
We're going to do this right now.
Because I want you to talk to
the program manager that's appropriate for your technology.
So, and the best way to do that,
if you think about these program managers, right,
they've got hundreds of calls
and people complaining to them,
give me money.
Why aren't you giving me money?
I'm so great.
Well,
I want you to do this.
And then I'm going to
tell you that I love this.
And I'm going to tell you that I love this.
They're going to say,
oh,
they're going to say,
well,
this is what some of my friends
call a love language for the SBIR community.
It's like a consistent way to kind of put your company and
your technology innovation in a format that's easy for them to digest.
And the reason why I want you guys to do this
is because I want you to have the best success possible.
So if you put it in a quad chart format
and send an introductory email to the program manager that's appropriate,
and you already know all this background,
then they're gonna say,
oh,
this person knows what they're doing.
They're going to,
they're going to follow the rules.
They're not going to waste my time.
This sounds like somebody that I really want to fund.
So I've got this quad chart here.
And I understand what they're doing.
It fits in the area.
And I can give them quick feedback.
And they're not going to ask
me a bunch of dumb questions
to keep me on the phone because they're
trying to be my friend.
So let's do that.
And once you have a call with a program manager
and describe to them what's on the quad chart
and the situation with the company and everything else,
then you can do the administrative work
and forming the company and everything else.
And as Ben says in his video, there's like sam.gov,
research.gov, spa.gov.
And it can take like 30 days to do that.
So to your question about
two months to write the proposal,
if you don't have any of this stuff registered yet,
it's another like 30 days to do it.
You can do that in parallel with writing the proposal.
I mean, you just submit stuff
and then you just wait for it.
One other comment I like to make is
that if you guys are in startup mode
and you're trying to decide, should I raise equity
or should I go for grants?
One of the wonderful things about grants
is that there's a deadline.
So you've got to get it
all done and get it submitted.
And then once it's in, there's nothing you can do.
You just have to sit back
and wait for them to review it,
which is a wonderful thing, frankly.
People are like, ah, you're waiting
and why am I taking it?
No, no, no.
You guys have 8,000 other things to do.
You get this done, it's like a homework assignment.
You've got to submit it, get
it in, and then you've got to.
And in fact, they often take a lot of time.
So you've got to get it done.
You've got to submit it, get
it in, and then you've got to.
And in fact, they often take a lot of time.
So you've got to get it done.
And a lot of comments, they often
don't want to be bothered after you submit it.
And that's like a negative.
So it's beneficial in both areas.
So a lot of times in companies, I'll say,
why don't you guys go
ahead and fill this proposal out,
submit it, and then go get busy with your investor
conversations and discussions.
Because what I didn't say
is that on the SBR side,
there's a deadline so that you can't do anything
after a certain date on that particular proposal.
But in the world of raising capital from investors,
there is no end to the
amount of meetings you could have
and the amount of follow-ups you could have.
So that becomes a gigantic time sink
if you don't manage your time carefully.
So I do want to say
that the solicitation, a lot of times
people will take information and they'll
try and sell it to you online and say, hey,
this is how this thing works.
And there's all kinds of consulting companies out there.
But the PDF that you download from the website that
is the solicitation, that's the official document.
And that's the legal document.
That's the ultimate source of facts.
So if you're looking for
the ground truth of how should
this grant be done or
how should this contract be done,
it should be in the solicitation.
And if it's not, then
you're going to ask the program
manager that.
OK.
So what I'd like to
do now is take 10 minutes.
And if you guys all have laptops,
you can download this quad
chart template, which is from 2018.
I realize it's old.
I'm going to start the timer now.
And then I'm going to take questions
while you guys all get busy on that stuff.
And we'll wait 10 minutes.
Yes.
Go ahead.
So we sent a letter to the program manager
and he had little response.
He said that we did not provide pre-submission tailored
feedback.
How do you get that feedback?
The feedback they said, get positive feedback.
You sent them like a detailed question.
Oh, yeah.
So OK.
So well, we're timing.
Everybody's doing their quad charts.
So the point of that
is once we finish this exercise
and you have your first call, there's
a few other steps that I'll
talk about in a second, which
is to go find the right guy
that you need to talk to or gal.
And then what you want
to get is this looks interesting.
This is exactly the type of stuff we would fund.
So go ahead and fill out an application for this.
That would be fantastic.
You may not get that.
You may get like, OK, it's
not terrible, which is kind of you
have to lean into that
and realize that that's a positive.
So not being told to go.
You know, like this is wrong is a good thing.
And you may also get just like,
hey, this is not the right thing.
We've done this eight times already.
And we've never had any success for it.
So don't bother, which is fantastic, right?
Because then you don't have to waste your time,
all this time trying to fill
out an application and for no avail.
So are they available for a call?
Because from what I got from this email,
it's kind of like, no, we don't give any feedback.
Oh, so they are available for a call,
but they may be wary about calling.
OK.
So they may not be giving you specific feedback
to make your proposal more competitive.
So you can ask them some questions,
but a lot of times they just won't answer.
And we can ask that of
Ben on Wednesday, by the way.
Feel free to ask him any questions you want.
And you'll get the fantastic answers like, excuse me,
like I'm not at liberty to discuss those things
or against certain rules, all that kind of stuff.
We've heard that it's also good to approach them,
but we've never gotten anyone to pick up our calls.
Probably because you didn't email them a quad chart ahead
of time and show them that you're awesome.
So other questions on this stuff
or you guys are busy digging in?
Yes.
So you mentioned that they're not allowed to give feedback
under certain circumstances.
But it looks like they can
if you just reach out to them.
So what's this ?
So they can't, I forget what the legal limitations are,
but they can't kind of tell you
that, hey, this is a good time,
but hey, yeah, we would totally fund this.
They can tell you that there's a match
or there's a good likelihood of match.
They can't give you any guidance around what to change.
But really what you're trying to do,
and I think I have a slide on this,
so I apologize for repeating it ahead of time,
is just develop a relationship with the funder.
And what I want you to do is I want
you to do it in the
right way and in the sort
of compatible way.
And I want you guys to
all do your homework ahead of time
so you don't ask silly questions
about what the other person is
doing.
Yeah.
So this is a good example
of what we're trying to do.
So we're trying to do what the program manager does
in terms of what the SBR program
does and all that kind of stuff.
But that you're trying to
get to those top three motivations
of the program manager.
They won't get fired.
They won't be embarrassed by funding your technology.
And they'll be excited about actually, like, oh,
this is cool stuff.
I mean, this is what we do.
I highly doubt you'll ever get any SBR program manager
to say, wow, this is really cool stuff.
We should fund this.
That's not in their DNA.
So OK.
I'm just filling out for the ID.
They are asking for the issue.
What was the question?
This fund is coming directly from the federal government,
or is it coming from federal government to some agency
and then to you?
Well, it's a federal agency.
So I guess it would
be coming from the federal government.
So there's a question that I'm applying for this ID
to apply directly for federal grants or loans.
Yes.
So it has to be yes.
I don't know.
You guys are supposed to be the smart ones that
can fill stuff out properly.
Any other questions on this?
Otherwise, I'll chill out for a few minutes while you.
So just one quick note.
If you notice, there's a company, state, name, email,
phone.
A lot of times people miss
that on the top of the thing.
Whoop.
We're not doing that again.
OK.
So that quad chart is for every technology.
And that even works with the National Science Foundation
as well.
The National Science Foundation has a new process
where you have to fill out a project pitch.
And I know one person in
the audience has done this already.
And what you'll notice is that the technology innovation,
the technology objectives, the market opportunity,
the company team is very similar
to the quad chart, just sort
of in paragraph format.
And I think because the NSF is a
company, it's going to be a lot more efficient.
And I think because the NSF is
so broad and has so much leverage
to fund a lot of things that
they decided to put this process up
front to make sure people didn't waste their time
and they didn't waste their time finding reviewers.
So you have to submit
a project pitch to them first.
And you have to select kind
of what area it goes in.
And until you get a sort of encouraged
to apply response from them, you
can't fill out a phase one.
So this is a necessary step in the overall process.
OK.
Thank you.
And these instructions are on that website.
So you can take a look at that as well.
So what I want you to
do after that is find the agency,
the solicitation dates, and contact information,
and prepare for a one-on-one call with the specific program
manager.
So to find the agency, you can go here.
I mean, SPR.gov has all this stuff.
But you can actually search for all the awards that
were funded previously and find something
that's similar to your technology.
And then search for the agency.
And then search for the agency that's funded.
And then within that agency, you find
if there's an open solicitation, the dates and deadlines,
and find the official PDF of that
and the specific topic for your technology.
And I'm talking about mission-focused ones now.
I know the broad-based ones, the market-focused ones,
will have very broad ones.
So it's fairly easy to read through their solicitation
and find where your technology would fit.
For the DOD ones that have 1,000 different solicitations,
you do have to go through
and find, kind of, at the local,
at the lower level, and then find the contact name
of the person that's going to fund that topic.
And that's the person that you
want to email your quad chart
to and set up a call with.
Because that's the person that wrote the solicitation,
got a bunch of people to input on,
like, what should the solicitation be?
And they're going to be the ones that
are going to convene a review panel
and look at your proposal.
So that's the person that you want to really
kind of be in contact with.
And of course, if there's a
question, you can go to the DOD.
There isn't actually a person on that solicitation,
which sometimes there isn't.
They usually have a general
SPR contact that you can say,
hey, this is my technology.
I'm interested in this topic.
Who should I speak with at the firm?
And of course, just using standard good sales process,
you send an email and you
follow up after a few days,
and then you follow up
after a few days after that,
and then you send another follow-up email and stuff.
So, okay.
So this all brings us to the homework
that you guys maybe are already done.
So what you're going to be done on, on Wednesday,
or you can even send it
in to me ahead of time.
There may be an extra prize
if you send it ahead of time.
You should already be familiar with the one-on-one stuff
from that video and from this talk,
but I want you to list
all the agencies and the topics
that potentially could fund your technology,
and then research other technologies that have funded there.
Have your complete quad chart done,
and then prepare questions for your call.
So what I would recommend your
call have is just general feedback.
the feedback of fit for your technology with their agency.
So making sure there isn't like some weird, you know,
oh, you didn't know about this other thing,
we don't actually fund that technology, right?
A fast no is a great
thing in this world because, you know,
there's all kinds of money out there.
And you want to really find,
find where you should focus at.
Building a relationship with the future funder.
And then you want to ask questions
and find out others you should talk to.
So that's the last question
that you want to ask them.
And often they'll say,
no I'm pretty much the only person which
is fine you know you could say that but
they might say like you should really
talk to this person or you should really
talk to this other person this is
the advanced tip is that those people are
probably also on the review panel for
your proposal so when you say oh that's
nice yeah I should talk to them too
yeah they don't have any money so why should
I talk to them well they can't tell
you they're on the review panel but more
than likely they will be or there's
some partner that you should really talk to
that they want to get their opinion of
so they may not officially be on the
review panel but if you get to
that point you definitely want to engage all
the people around that any of those
people mentioned so I did I did mess
this up one time when somebody was
like you should really talk to this person
and I was like I don't have time
for that and then you know we didn't get
funded I'm like oh because that was the
key person that was gonna weigh in on
our proposal to say yes or no dang
it so okay so that's the homework for Wednesday
on Wednesday
were going to continue and then we were
gonna continue on the rest of the week
we're going to talk about all of
the wonderful AI tools that make this whole
process way easy. And if you want to submit your,
your material to me early,
I might give you access to some of
those cool tools upfront before we get too
far down the pathway. So just as
a, just as an incentive there, um,
questions on this.
So yes, do we send the, uh,
the homework to these, uh, email address?
Yes. Send it to me. You can
send it to steve at co foundry.global,
or you can send it to sjd
at mit.edu or I have a million emails.
Okay. Questions on any of that stuff.
We're almost done here guys. So please,
please bring up the questions. Everything's
good. Ready to rock and roll.
Anxious to get AI to
help you do all this stuff.
Well, I will,
I will say one thing which is
that, and I'll probably repeat this on Wednesday,
so maybe I shouldn't say it
now, but anyways, I'll say anyways, uh,
what I've found is that AI gets you
from kind of an F to a B,
and then it really takes humans to get
you from a B to like an A,
A plus where you actually get funded, right?
Where funding level is a, so, so no,
you can't have AI is just go and get
you, go get me a bunch of money, right?
Like that's fantasy land. Um,
and I,
I would highly recommend that you guys
ask Ben that question when he gets on
the, when he gets on the call on,
on Wednesday, like how do you, you know,
do you encourage AI usage? Um, I mean,
ultimately it's people funding people. So,
and people can still tell that
it's an AI behind the scenes.
Especially if you have a phone call with them,
they're going to know that you're not
an AI or a human. So, um,
and then this is the,
this is the agenda we'll go
over timing and calendar management and applying
while in school. Um,
I do want to talk
about a budget example because the,
a lot of times the budget
is important in the review process. Um,
that's a sanity check about
here's what you're proposing to do.
Here's the cool technology. Here's the market opportunity.
Here's the team that you have working on it.
And then why are you giving all
this money to that guy? You know,
like forget it, you know, that's, that's
obviously you had it all lined up,
but your budget doesn't match with what your intention is.
So as long as you've got like a
good plan and it's like, Oh, well, clearly the,
the key technology guy needs to
get a bulk of the budget,
then that makes all the sense in
the world. So we'll talk about that. Um,
and then we'll talk about the review
process in a little more detail. Uh,
and then I've got a whole bunch of, uh,
gendered Bay stuff and then the last
I think half hour of the class,
we'll have a chance to chat with
Ben on the call. So questions on that.
Yeah. Um, I've heard that
there's some audit that takes place.
I do have to have some,
yeah. Can you talk a little bit about that?
Sure. Sure. I mean, we'll talk
about it more on Wednesday, but, uh,
there's something called a CAAR, a car.
I think it's like audit and accounting.
I'll just cut to the chase.
Okay. There's a whole bunch of stuff.
The hardest part that everybody in your shoes
has to deal with is that if you
are spending the government's money,
you have to show that you're allocating it correctly.
How do you show that you're
allocating correctly? I'm paying for people's time.
How do I show that
I'm paying for people's time correctly?
I'm keeping time cards.
So if you have a proper time
cards keeping system in your accounting system,
and you're allocating it to the
right people for the right amount,
and you have proof of that and you have
sign off on that, then you pass the car.
So that's, this is for
phase two now. So this is,
you've already got the phase one,
and you're trying to you basically apply for phase two.
You go through the review process,
you get approved, you get like, Hey,
we wanna fund this, but you have to go through,
go through the due diligence checklist, which means,
are you a real company? You know, what's
your accounting system? What's your, you know,
financial prospects and all that good stuff?
And can you manage this fund? Because it's,
you know, it's a million bucks, right? It's not,
it's not just a few hundred thousand bucks. So
it's a lot more money, a lot more time.
So they want to run you through a lot
more diligence at that phase to, to make sure you're
okay to get the funding. So, and the DOD
is even harder. So there's a, there's a whole,
I forget what it's called, DFAS or something
like that, that makes you go through a whole
bunch of audits and stuff. I've done it. So
I can, that's why I'm grabbing my head because
I'm getting headaches right now. So let's break.
I'm going to say the other questions. Any other
questions? Yes. What about accelerated track that you can
stop at phase one and two, at least for
NIH, I know, because I don't know
others. Yes. Do you recommend such thing?
So the fast track usually is a lot
more popular because everybody's like, well, I'm going to
waste my time with a hundred thousand bucks. And then
I get a chance to get a million bucks. Like,
why can't I do it all at once? And I'm
like, well, I'm going to waste my time with a hundred
all at once. That means that there's
more applications and there's a lower chance of
success. That is exactly what a conversation
with a program manager would be like, Hey,
we're thinking about applying for phase one. We're
not sure about SBR, STTR. We're also thinking
about fast track, you know, where would this
be best fit? Right. And usually fast track,
it means that you've already got the commercial
partners lined up for phase two. So it's like,
I'm ready to kind of go to phase two. So I
want to jam all this stuff together. And you, you have
to be like totally kick.
Ass to do the fast track stuff. So there's
a lot of examples where people are just like,
they're perfectly aligned with the solicitation
that came out. So it's like,
we don't want to waste our time doing a phase
one and phase two. We want to just go at it.
And that's that, that those are great
candidates for fast track. So other questions.
All right, guys. Thank you. See you Wednesday.
Bye.